Guide to the American Association of University Women Portland Branch records
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
American Association of University Women Portland Branch records
1906-2023
Oregon Historical Society Research Library
American Association of University Women. Portland (Or.) Branch
Mss 2964
14.5 cubic feet 10 record cartons; 5 letter document cases; 2 legal document cases; 2 slim letter document cases; 2 flat boxes (11x14); 1 flat box (13x16)
1 gigabytes 1,933 digital files
Records and memorabilia of the Portland, Oregon, branch of the American Association of University Women (AAUW), as well as records of its parent organizations, AAUW of Oregon and the national AAUW. The AAUW Portland Branch was founded in 1905, and throughout its history has advocated for women's college education and equitable treatment.
Collection is open for research.
Gifts of the American Association of University Women Portland Branch made from 1992 to 2023 (Lib. Acc. 20793; Lib. Acc. 22691; Lib. Acc. 26576; Lib. Acc. 27553; RL2022-154; RL2023-039).
Collection is arranged in six series:
Series 1: Administrative records
Series 2: Compiled records and memorabilia
Series 3: Special projects and activism
Series 4: Event records and memorabilia
Series 5: Newsletters
Series 6: Parent organization records and memorabilia
The Portland, Oregon, branch of the American Association of University Women (AAUW; initially named Association of Collegiate Alumnae) was founded in 1905 by Elizabeth C. Chapman Donald. Throughout its history, the branch has raised funds for scholarships and fellowships for women, and has advocated for women's education and equity.
In 1918, the branch was one of several women's organizations that raised funds to found the Waverly Baby Home. In the 1930s, the branch offered a "Free Time School" for young women who were unable to attend college. During World War II, its members helped found and staff a "baby lounge" at Union Station where parents who were traveling with young children could rest and see to their children's needs while waiting between trains; it was one of four such facilities in the U.S. Starting in 1954, the branch published a catalog of local nurseries, daycares, and kindergartens. In the 1950s, branch president Marion Stearns advocated for the establishment of an educational television station in Portland, culminating in legislation to fund the Oregon Public Broadcasting System in 1959. In 1973, the branch published a book about Oregon history, "Land of the Multnomahs," as a fundraiser for fellowship programs.
Sources: Articles in the Oregonian and Oregon Journal, 1944-1980; "Women of This World: Portland, Oregon, Branch American Association of University Women, 1905-1979," by Lynn Jordan, 1980.
An index to digital files for this collection is located in Box 15, Folder 7.
Access to audio and video materials and to digital files on CDs requires specialized equipment. Digital files not on CDs are available upon request. Contact library staff for assistance.
Additional materials at the Oregon Historical Society Research Library relating to the American Association of University Women Portland Branch are in the vertical file, Clubs - Women's Clubs.
The collection consists of the records of the Portland, Oregon, branch of the American Association of University Women (AAUW). In addition to administrative records, the collection includes memorabilia in the form of scrapbook pages with newspaper clippings, photographs, and ephemera; newsletters; materials relating to the branch's history and individual members; and materials relating to the branch's activities, including its scholarships and fellowships, its operation of a "baby lounge" during World War II, and anniversary celebrations.
The collection also contains records of the branch's parent organizations, the AAUW of Oregon and the national AAUW. The AAUW of Oregon's records include convention programs and bound volumes of policies, minutes, and newsletters. The national AAUW records include correspondence sent to the Portland Branch, and reports published by the organization, particularly by its Educational Foundation.
The bulk of photographs from Lib. Acc. 20793 and Lib. Acc. 26576 were processed as the American Association of University Women Portland Branch photographs, Org. Lot 1360, Oregon Historical Society Research Library.
American Association of University Women. Portland (Or.) Branch--Records and correspondence; American Association of University Women--Records and correspondence; American Association of University Women. Oregon Division--Records and correspondence; American Association of University Women. Oregon Division; American Association of University Women
Clubs--Oregon--Portland; Women--Oregon--Portland--Societies and clubs; Women--Education--Oregon--Portland
Clubs and Societies; Women
administrative records; correspondence; newsletters; scrapbooks
- Administrative records, 1915-2023; Series 1
  Audio materials in this series require specialized equipment to access. Digital files in this series are available upon request. Contact library staff for assistance.
  - Constitution, circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution, 1943 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Revisions to constitution, circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bylaws, 1969-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Bylaws, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bylaws, 2004-2008 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bylaws and policies, 2008-2018 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bylaws, 2012-2014; 2023 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bylaws, bylaw drafts, and policies (digital files), 2015-2023
  - Bylaws and policies, 2019-2023 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - AAUW affiliate agreement, 2009 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - AAUW affiliate agreement (digitized copy), 2009 October 15
  - Meeting minutes, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
  - Meeting minutes and related records, 1938-1948 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Meeting minutes, 1948-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14-16)
  - Meeting minutes and related records, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
  - Meeting agendas, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Meeting minutes and related records, 1964-1967 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - Meeting minutes, 1968-1986 (Box 1, Folder 22-31)
  - Meeting minutes and related records, 1987-1990 (Box 1, Folder 32-33)
  - Meeting minutes and agendas, 1994-2001 (Box 1, Folder 34-38)
  - Meeting minutes, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 39-40)
  - Meeting minutes and agendas, 2003-2004 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Meeting minutes, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Meeting minutes and agendas, 2006-2013 (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
  - Meeting minutes, agendas, and related records, 2013-2019 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Meeting minutes, agendas, and related records (digital files), 2008-2023
  - Notice and minutes of Interbranch Council meeting (digital files), 2017
  - Audio recordings of meetings (36 microcassettes), 2006-2009 (Box 13)
  - Audio recordings of meetings (3 cassettes), undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - Unlabeled audio recordings, most likely of meetings, undated (Box 14, Folder 2-3)
  - Education Committee meeting minutes, circa 1943 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Legislative Action Group meeting minutes, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Legislative Action Group records, 1946-1949 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Policy Committee records, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Radio Program Committee records, 1940-1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Scholarship Committee minutes book, 1918-1929 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Study group records, circa 1940-1949 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Study group information, 1963-1964; 1978; 1999; 2015 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Study group reports, 1947-1953 (Box 2, Folder 9-11)
  - Study group reports, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Study group reports, 1965-1970 (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
  - Study group reports, 1973-1990 (Box 2, Folder 16-21)
  - Correspondence, 1917-1928 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Renee D. Bergman correspondence, 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Letter from Elizabeth Plankinton to Esther Adamson, 1957 June 7 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Correspondence, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Correspondence, 1996-2012 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence (digital files), 2022
  - Financial records, 1939-1948 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Budgets, 1963; 1969-1973 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Financial reports, 1966-1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Budgets and financial reports, 1994-2006 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Financial records, 2005-2018 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Financial records (digital files), 2014-2018
  - Membership directories, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Membership directories, 1961-2015 (Box 2, Folder 33-41)
  - Membership directories, 2016-2018; 2022 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Membership dues records, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Membership records, 2006-circa 2019 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Membership records (digital files), 2013-2023
  - Membership survey, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Branch reports, 1940-1942; 1948 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Branch reports, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Branch reports, 1965-1966 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Branch report, circa 1970 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - President's reports, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - President's report, circa 1935 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - President's reports, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Secretary's report, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Secretary's reports, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Committee reports, 1919-1924 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Community representative's report, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Parent education reports, 1939 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Education reports, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Branch historian's report, 1951 April 10 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - UNESCO chair's report, circa 1949 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Vice president in charge of study groups' report, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Consumer study report about milk control laws in Oregon, circa 1949 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Unsorted reports, 1939-1942 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Unsorted reports, 2000-2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Reports (digital files), 2010-2023
  - Board rosters, 1992-2005 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Board of directors attendance record, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Brochure about fundraising staff, 2019 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Certificate for most improved bulletin presented at the state convention, 1983 April 23 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Branch goals for 2001-2002 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Form letters for new members, circa 2004; 2008 August (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Design for branch centennial logo, 2005 (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Records relating to donation of records to the Oregon Historical Society (digital files), 2008
  - Guidelines and scripts for installation of branch officers, 2016 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Scripts for installation of branch officers (digital files), 2016-2020
  - List of co-presidents' duties for officers and committees, 2017 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - List of co-presidents' duties for officers and committees (digital files), 2015-2017
  - Draft of President Eleanor Krause's message, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Notes about branch activities, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Unsorted notes, circa 1975 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Organization chart, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Proposed policy for named gift honorees, circa 1995 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Recommendations for project reviews, circa 1941 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Recommendations to board, 1980 April 10 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Strategic planning records (digital files), 2015-2017
  - Suggestions for restatement of the constitution of the Adult Education Council, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Suggested content for newsletters, 2018 April (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Website proposal, circa 2002 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Indexes of filed administrative records, 1940-1942 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Index to digital files, 2023 (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - List of records destroyed and records retained during file cleanout (digital file), 2014 November 1
- Compiled records and memorabilia, 1906-2023; Series 2
  This series consists of materials that branch members, often the president, secretary, or historian, gathered specifically for historical preservation, as well as information produced about the branch's history. The contents of this series may overlap with or duplicate materials in other series.
  Digital files in this series are available upon request. Contact library staff for assistance.
  - Compiled information about branch's early history, 1906-circa 1930 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - History of the branch by Jane Lancaster (digital file), undated
  - History of the branch by Ilga Ross (digital file), 2021 May
  - Correspondence, records, and ephemera compiled by presidents Elizabeth C. Plankinton and Ethel E. Hewitt, 1932-1937 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, records, and ephemera compiled by presidents Anne Mulheron and Pauline S. Kiehle, 1939-1942 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence and records compiled by President Nell A. Unger, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Records, clippings, correspondence, event programs, newsletters, photograph, and slides compiled by branch historian, 1940-1979 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Records, clippings, and member biographies compiled by Branch Historian Clara Bristol, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Compiled records, clippings, and ephemera, 1966-1975 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Records compiled by President Judy Buffo, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Records and memorabilia compiled by President Mary Betty Underwood, 1978-1980 (Box 3, Folder 45-48)
  - Records compiled by President Bernice "Bea" Severson, 1992-1993 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Compiled records, 1992; 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Compiled materials, including administrative records, clippings, newsletters, and photographs, 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Compiled materials, including meeting minutes, newsletters, and photographs, 1996-1998 (Box 3, Folder 52-53)
  - Compiled records, 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Compiled materials, including meeting minutes and agendas, correspondence, reports, and newsletters, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 55-56)
  - Compiled materials, including correspondence, newsletters, photographs, administrative records, brochures, and ephemera, 1998-2000 (Box 3, Folder 57-58)
  - Compiled records, including meeting minutes and agendas, financial records, reports, and correspondence, 2011-2023 (Box 4, Folder 1-6)
  - Drafts, script, and notes about branch's history, circa 1949-1965 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Notecards and clippings about branch history, circa 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Photograph of branch members, circa 1925 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of branch members, circa 1939-1941 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of branch activities, 1992-1994 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Photographs of branch activities (digital files), 2008-2016
  - Photo history book of branch activities from 2008 to 2019 by Ilga Ross, 2019 June (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Publication about branch's history by Lynn Jordan, "Women of This World: Portland, Oregon, Branch American Association of University Women 1905-1979" (original), 1980 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Publication about branch's history by Lynn Jordan, "Women of This World: Portland, Oregon, Branch American Association of University Women 1905-1979" (photocopy), 1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Publicity report and compiled clippings and newsletters, 1961-1964 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Publicity report and compiled clippings, newsletters, and records, 1964-1967 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Compiled clippings and ephemera, 1976-1978 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook pages with clippings, newsletters, records, photographs, directories, and ephemera, 1951-1991 (Box 4, Folder 16-25)
  - Scrapbook pages with clippings and newsletters, 1953-1954 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Scrapbook pages with clippings, newsletters, directories, and photograph, 1956-1957 (Box 16, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook pages with clippings, newsletters, records, and nursery catalog, 1957 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Scrapbook pages with clippings, newsletters, correspondence, and ephemera, 1957-1960 (Box 17, Folder 1-2)
  - Scrapbook pages with clippings and newsletters, 1958-1959 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook pages with clippings and records, 1968-1976 (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Scrapbook pages with clippings, photographs, press releases, and holiday card, 1977-1988 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Scrapbook of photographs, ephemera, and clippings, 1992-1994 (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Historian's scrapbook, including records, directories, newsletters, photographs, and ephemera, 2000-2003 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Scrapbook pages of newsletter clippings, 2014 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Script for skit about branch's history, written by Meda Johnson, 1966 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Timeline of branch history, 2005 (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Information about notable branch members from 1950 to 1981, circa 1981 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Biographical information about branch founder Elizabeth C. Chapman Donald, circa 2015 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Clipping and biographical information about branch founder Elizabeth C. Chapman Donald (digitized item and digital file), 1955; circa 2018
  - Biographical information about member Eileen Eliott (digital files), 2015
  - Papers and memorabilia of and relating to Ruth Haefner, including newsletters, photographs, clippings, correspondence, obituaries, and materials relating to the Gray Panthers, 1973-1988 (Box 5, Folder 7-8)
  - Eulogy for Ardis Hitchcock and records relating to the Ardis Hitchcock Memorial Fund, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Obituary for Naomi Paschelke, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Obituary and memorial service program for Gail "Doty" Post, 2014 January (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Biographical information about member Ilga Ross (digital files), 2016-2017
  - Papers of Julie Skinner, including correspondence, certificates, and Oregon-Washington dual convention flyer and lunch program, 2008-2014 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Obituary for Patricia Green Swenson, 2010 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Clippings about and memorial service program for Phyllis Wiener; essay that in part discusses Wiener, 1975-1979; 1976 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Compiled clippings, 1916-1937 (Box 11, Folder 6-8)
  - Compiled clippings, 1937-1941 (Box 12, Folder 1-2)
  - Compiled clippings, 1942-1949 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Compiled clippings, 1949-1961 (Box 12, Folder 3-4)
  - Compiled clippings, 1964-1967 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Compiled clippings, circa 1981-1990 (Box 12, Folder 6)
- Special projects and activism, circa 1930-2022; Series 3
  A significant portion of this series concerns scholarships and fellowships that the branch funded. Other projects include a series of essays written about the arts in Portland; materials relating to the "baby lounge" that the branch operated at Union Station during World War II; catalogs the branch published, listing local nurseries, day cares, and kindergartens; and materials relating to "Land of the Multnomahs," a history book it published as a fundraiser.
  - Art in Portland research project: Introduction, sculpture, and painting, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Art in Portland research project: Architecture, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Art in Portland research project: Literature, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Art in Portland research project: Music, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Art in Portland research project: Theater, dance, and film, 1940 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Date books for baby lounge, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 20-21)
  - Baby lounge: Lists of workers and expenses, circa 1944 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Baby lounge: Notes, 1944-1945 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Clippings about baby lounge, 1944 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Script of radio drama by creative writing group, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Book of poetry by creative writing group, 1963 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - History of AAUW fellowships, circa 1940 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Lists of scholarship beneficiaries from 1906 to 1928, circa 1930 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Definitions of types of AAUW fellowships, undated (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Script for play about fellowships, "A Fellowship Pageant", 1934 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Digitized scrapbook pages with script for "A Fellowship Pageant" and related notes and clippings (digital files, titled as "Fundraising Play 1920s"), 1934
  - Records and clippings about fellowships, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Records, brochures, event programs, clippings, and ephemera about fellowships, 1963-1994 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Correspondence about fellowships, 1968-1972 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence and photocopied clippings relating to sculptor Mary Lewis, a Mabel Merwin Fellowship recipient, 1950-2006 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Records about Phyllis Wiener Scholarship, 1984-1986 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Records relating Portland Community College scholarships (digital files), 2014-2018
  - Agreement for Portland Community College scholarship endowment (digital file), 2022 June 7
  - Records relating to partnerships and relations with colleges and universities (digital files), 2016-2017
  - Reports, correspondence, and clipping about Free-Time School, 1933-1934 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence, report, and clippings about High School International Relations Club, circa 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence and statement about housing measure, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Clippings and summary about inheritance tax reform bill, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence, notes, clippings, programs, and ephemera relating to fundraising for the Portland Junior Museum, 1948-1949 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Copyright registration and invitation to autograph tea for "Land of the Multnomahs", 1973 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Title page of "Land of the Multnomahs" with member autographs (photocopy), 1973 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Records and correspondence for Magazines for Friendship project in the Pacific Area, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence relating to project to reproduce a 1929 map of Oregon produced by the branch, 2001-2002 (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Nursery school and daycare catalogs, 1956; 1967-1975 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Nursery school, kindergarten, and daycare catalog, 1964 March (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Preschool, kindergarten, and daycare catalogs, 1978-1981 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Records relating to public policy (digital files), 2016
  - Preschool and daycare catalogs: Notes, draft for cover, and memo about distribution and availability, circa 1985 (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Scripts and correspondence relating to radio programs about the branch's activities and education, 1939-1942 (Box 5, Folder 47-49)
  - Records relating to STEM (science, technology, engineering, mathematics) project (digital files), 2011-2018
  - Letter from Legislative and Education committees to Oregon governor and legislation about teacher education, 1953 March 24 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Records, clippings, and other materials relating to the Reed Community Education Project, a tutoring program, 1964-1966 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Branch statement for United Nations' 25th anniversary, 1970 November 18 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and records relating to Portland's Walk of Heroines, 2008 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Records, correspondence, and press releases about war relief efforts, 1940-1942 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence and records relating to Young Scholars program, 2007-2010 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Invitations and programs for Young Scholars recognition celebrations, 2008-2010 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Unsorted records and correspondence relating to special projects and activism, 1939-1979 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Activities and events, 1923-2018; Series 4
  Digital files on CD in this series require specialized equipment to view. Digital files not on CD are available upon request. Contact library staff for assistance.
  - Report and newspaper clipping about 50th anniversary celebration (photocopies), 1955 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Programs, invitations, historical timeline, newsletter, and ephemera relating to centennial celebration luncheon, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Photographs of centennial celebration (digital photos on 1 CD), 2005 (Box 15, Folder 1)